Theatre of Light and Shadow: A Company of Women Records, 1978-1984
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Theatre of Light and Shadow records
1978-1984
Theatre of Light and Shadow
MS 370
11 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Theater company. An innovative women's theatre company, the Theatre of Light and Shadow was dedicated to theatre as both art and communication and to feminism as a lifestyle. Materials include correspondence, publicity, programs, scripts, and photographs.
The Theatre of Light and Shadow was founded in l977 by K.D. Codish, Belinda Beezley, and Ruth Beaumont and incorporated in l980. As an innovative women's theatre company, it was dedicated to theatre as both art and communication and to feminism as a lifestyle. In addition to performances the theatre conducted workshops, performed for other feminist activities, and served as a liaison with other organizations to promote opportunities for women in the arts. The group disbanded in August l983.
The Records of the Theatre of Light and Shadow: a Company of Women (TLS) consist of 5 linear feet of correspondence, notes, publicity, programs, financial records, printed ephemera, scripts, and photographs. They span the years 1978 to 1984 and describe the company's activities and administration as well as performances and conferences.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Administration
II. Activities
Miscellaneous Scripts
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The records were donated in June l986 by Nancy Lee Kathan, business manager of the Theatre of Light and Shadow.
Search Terms
Women in the theater--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminist theater--History--Sources; Theatre of Light and Shadow--History--Sources; Women dramatists, American--20th century--Sources
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  This series contains six sections: Organization, Personnel, Financial, Publicity, Meetings and Correspondence. The Organization section contains two notebooks (1979-1981) used by the staff of TLS. These were kept intact and contain incorporation materials, by-laws, tax and grant information, resumes, and audience questionnaires. Also in this section are rehearsal and production space contracts, agreements, and invoices. Personnel contains resumes, correspondence, clippings, notes, articles, and job descriptions for 6 principals of TLS plus general membership lists and requirements for the company as a whole. Financial consists of reports, budgets, expenditures, income statements, plus foundation correspondence, notes, applications, and brochures. Publicity contains TLS brochure photographs and graphics as well as general clippings and miscellaneous publicity. The Meetings section contains notes and agenda for general company meetings. The Correspondence is general in nature, to and from TLS, and arranged chronologically.
- SERIES II. ACTIVITIES
  This series contains two sections; Performances and Conferences. Performances is arranged chronologically (1978-1983) and includes photographs, reviews, programs, publicity, scripts, and evaluations for individual performances. Included also in this section are scripts received by TLS for possible production. The two conferences in the Conferences section are Women's Health Weekend and Women in Theatre. TLS participated in the Women's Health Weekend, and the records contain the program and publicity. Women in Theatre was a major conference sponsored by TLS in 1982 with a grant from the Connecticut Humanities Council. The records include organizational correspondence, publicity, scripts, the participants' resumes and evaluations, reel to reel tapes and transcripts of the sessions, Connecticut Humanities Council correspondence, proposals, and expenditures; and, finally, audience evaluations of the conference.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - Organization
    - Notebook containing incorporation, papers, by-laws, IRS material, 1979-82 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notebook containing grant information, audience questionnaires, resumes, 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rehearsal and production space: contracts, invoices, agreements, 1978-82 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personnel
    - Nancy Lee Kathan, business manager
      - Resume, job-related correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - City of New Haven Commission on Cultural Affairs: correspondence, meetings, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - K.D. Codish, artistic director, business manager and founder: clippings, articles about her, notes, 1980-83 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Marion Visel, development consultant: resumes, notes, job description, 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Belinda Beezley, Karen Bernstein, Ruth Beaumont: clippings about them, 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General: lists, resumes, job description, membership requirements, 1978-83 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial
    - Reports, budgets, 1980-81 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Expenditures, income statements, 1979-83 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous funding information and correspondence, 1980-81 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Foundations
      - Business Opportunities (marketing project): correspondence, notes, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Connecticut Commission on the Arts: correspondence, brochures, notes, 1981-83 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        [Connecticut Humanities Council--See: Women in Theatre Conference, Boxes 10-11]
      - Haymarket People's Fund: correspondence, notes, applications, brochures, 1981-82 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - New Haven Foundation, Arts Challenge Fund: correspondence, notes, drafts, 1980-81 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publicity
    - Brochure
      - Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Clippings, 1978-83 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Graphics, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Meetings
    - Notes (notebook including a section entitled TLS records in chronoligical order 7/31/79-7/2/80), 1979 Sep 24-1980 Ju1 14 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes, 1979-81 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Agenda, notices, 1981 Sept-1982 Nov (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1978 Feb-1983 Sept, undated (Box 3, Folder 25-27)
- SERIES II. ACTIVITIES
  - Performances
    - "Voices": program, reviews, 2 photographs, 1978 Apr-May (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Second Round": reviews, program, performance and production notes, 1978 Sept (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - "Clue in the Old Birdbath", 1979 Apr-Jun
      - Publicity, script, 10 photographs (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Audience evaluations (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Take Back the Night March: publicity, 1979 Jul (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - "Water Cycle": program, 1979 Aug (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - "In the Gloaming, Oh My Darling": publicity notes, photograph, 1979 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - "An Afternoon of Short Pieces":program, 1980 Feb (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - "The Woman Warrior": publicity, 1980 Mar (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "Can't You Take a Joke?": script, publicity correspondence, program, photograph, 1980 May (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "This Brooding Sky", 1980 Jul
      - Publicity, script, expenses (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Audience evaluations (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - "Recipe": script, 1980 Aug (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - "Connecticut Women": publicity,correspondence, 1981 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Five Plays", 1981 May-Jun
      - Publicity, finances (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Audience evaluations (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - "TLS Showcase": scripts, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Take Back the Night March: "Three Victims": script, correspondence, 1981 Sept (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - "Summer Salon", 1982 Jul-Aug
      - General publicity (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Performances
        - Program, script, photographs, 1982 Jul 7 (Box 4, Folder 48)
        - Program, script, notes, 1982 Jul 14 (Box 4, Folder 49)
        - Program, script, notes, 1982 Jul 21 (Box 4, Folder 50)
        - Program, script, notes, 1982 Jul 28 (Box 4, Folder 51)
        - Program, script, notes, 1982 Aug 4 (Box 4, Folder 52)
        - Program, scripts, 1982 Aug 6 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - "The Women Here Are No Different", 1982 Nov
      - Publicity
        - Press releases, graphics, notes, 4 photographs, miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 54)
        - Advertisement agreements (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - Scripts (Box 5, Folder 56)
      - Auditions, cast and crew lists, personnel (Box 5, Folder 57)
      - Tour 1983 Feb-Apr
        - New England Theatre Conference: program (Box 5, Folder 58)
        - Notes, correspondence, press releases, miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 59)
        - Production information: notes, financial reports, rehearsal space, miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - "Winter Salon", 1983 Feb 2-23
      - Publicity (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Script for performances (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "That's Not Funny": scripts, 1983 Mar 5 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Miscellaneous performances (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Unidentified production notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Miscellaneous scripts 1983 Feb 2-23 (Box 6-7)
      [See Miscellaneous Scripts]
  - Conferences
    - Women's Health Weekend: program, publicity, 1979 Apr (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Women in Theatre, 1982 Feb 24-Mar 31
      - Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 67)
      - Publicity
        - Brochure (Box 8, Folder 68)
        - Clippings, press releases (Box 8, Folder 69)
        - Programs (Box 8, Folder 70)
      - Scripts (Box 8, Folder 71)
      - Participants
        - Correspondence A-Z (Box 8, Folder 72-73)
        - Resumes (Box 8, Folder 74)
        - Transcripts of papers (Box 8, Folder 75)
        - Evaluations (Box 8, Folder 76)
        - Permissions for videotaping (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Miscellaneous notes and unidentified material (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Tapes (Box 9)
    - Connecticut Humanities Council
      - Organization of project (Box 10, Folder 79)
      - Grant proposals, related correspondence and printed material (Box 10, Folder 80)
      - Expenditures and budget reports (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Audience evaluations (Box 11, Folder 82-88)
- MISCELLANEOUS SCRIPTS
  - Scripts in Box 6
    - Ausubel, Bobbi. "Focus on Me" (Box 6)
    - Brady, Maureen. "I Know A Hundred Ways To Die" (Box 6)
    - Churchill, Caryl. "Vinegar Tom" (Box 6)
    - Crawford, Olive & Rori Reber, Penelope Stella, Judith Utevsky. "Intrusions," 1980 (Box 6)
    - Fagen, Patricia. "Dolls" (Box 6)
    - Gems, Pam. "Dusa, Fish, Stas & Vi" (Box 6)
    - Goldemberg, Rose Leiman. "Letters Home" (Box 6)
    - Goodman, Wendy-Marie. "Nazi Dreams," 1980 (Box 6)
    - Green, Phyllis. "Acapulco Holiday" (Box 6)
    - Hairston, Andrea. "Locked Out Of The World," 1982 (Box 6)
    - Lee, Maryat. "Puse," 1971 (Box 6)
    - McDonough, Kaye. "Zelda," 1978 (Box 6)
    - Miller, Susan. "Confessions Of A Female Disorder" (Box 6)
    - Norman, Marsha. "The Laundromat," 1978 (Box 6)
    - Plays by the Women's Repertory Theatre Company of Long Island and Collected Short Plays by Nicholas White (Box 6)
    - Simmons, Lydia. "When Other Friendships Have Been Forgot" (Box 6)
  - Scripts in Box 7
    - Westbeth Playwrights Feminist Collective (Box 7)
    - Wilshire, Donna. "Daughters Of Liberty" (Box 7)
    - Unidentified scripts (Box 7)